<document>
<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

<body>
    <section name="Cayenne FAQ">
    	<p>Note that Cayenne FAQ is created using WikiWiki collaboration technology.
    	Anyone can participate in creation of the FAQ by going to 
    	<a href="http://c2.com/cgi-bin/wiki?CayenneFaq">http://c2.com/cgi-bin/wiki?CayenneFaq</a>. 
    	Current page contains more or less complete snapshot of the WikiWiki page.
		</p>
 
 		<subsection name="cayenne.xml is not found">
 			<p><strong>Q.:</strong> After installation, an application using Cayenne
 			gives an error similar to 
 			<code>"ConfigException: [org.objectstyle.cayenne.conf.DefaultConfiguration] : 
 			Domain configuration file "cayenne.xml" is not found.", even though cayenne.xml
 			is in the CLASSPATH.</code></p>
 			
 			<p><strong>A.:</strong> Most likely this happened due to the fact that application 
 			classes and Cayenne classes are loaded by different ClassLoaders
 			and Cayenne configuration package can't access configuration
 			files accessible to application ClassLoader. 
 			Typical reason for that is when cayenne.jar is placed in extensions
 			directory of the JVM ($JRE_HOME/lib/ext directory). In this case
 			programmer must explicitly bootstrap Cayenne to look for configuration
 			files in the right place. This can be done by the following code
 			(it can be added to "main" method of the applicaton for instance):	
 	     	</p>
 			
			<source>
// let Cayenne know about the default application ClassLoader
Configuration.bootstrapSharedConfig(MyClass.class);
</source>
			</subsection>
			
			
			<subsection name="How do I log an output of a single query.">
 			<p><strong>Q.:</strong>  How do I log an output of a single query.</p>
 			
 			<p><strong>A.:</strong> Cayenne allows to control logging levels of 
 			individual queries and commits using the Apache log4j API. 
 			For instance to log the execution of a select query do something like this:
			</p>
<source>
SelectQuery q = new SelectQuery();
q.setLogLevel(Level.WARN);
List objects = dataContext.performQuery(q);
</source>
			<p>To log commit execution do this:</p>
<source>
dataContext.commitChanges(Level.WARN);	
</source>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name="How do I report a bug I found in Cayenne.">
 			<p><strong>Q.:</strong>  How do I report a bug I found in Cayenne.</p>
 			
 			<p><strong>A.:</strong> Cayenne is using SourceForge bug tracking system. 
 			Go to <a href=
 			"http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=48132&amp;atid=452068">http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=48132&amp;atid=452068</a> 
 			to submit Cayenne-related bugs. Reporting bugs is the most valuable contribution
 			Cayenne users can provide for the development team.
			</p>
			</subsection>
    </section>
</body>
</document>
