<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>TODO</title>

    <properties>
        <author>Andrei Adamchik</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <!-- News section -->
        <section name="How Can I Help">
        <p>Every volunteer project gets its strength from its participants.
        We invite everybody interested to participate in Cayenne.        
        If you are willing to help, this can be done in many different ways:
        <ul>
            <li>By contributing code.</li> 
            <li>By contributing documentation.</li> 
            <li>By testing Cayenne and reporting bugs.</li>
            <li>By using Cayenne and reporting bugs.</li>
            <li>By suggesting your own ideas on the mailing list and contributing
            code implementing them.</li>
        </ul>        
        </p>
        
        <p>If you want to become a contributor, first you should probably subscribe to 
        <a href="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/lists.html">Cayenne Developer Mailing List.</a>
        to see what issues are discussed and to communicate with the project team.
        Normally code and documentation contributions are made via patches sent
        to developer list. If your contributions are significant and you are willing 
        to join the core team, current committers can vote to give you CVS write access 
        and other committer rights.</p>
        
        http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=48132
        
        <subsection name="How to Create a Patch">
        <p>Preferred way to create a patch is to <a href="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=48132">check 
        out Cayenne source tree</a> via anonymous CVS,
        make changes to the local copy, and then run the following command (GUI CVS clients
        usually have support for this feature as well):
        </p>
<source>
cd cayenne
cvs diff -u > patch.txt
</source>

		<p>Resulting <code>patch.txt</code> file will contain changes to all Cayenne files
		as compared to the latest CVS version. Patches should be submitted via <a href="bugs-features.html">Cayenne 
		Issue Tracker</a> . There is no need to notify cayenne-devel mailing list, since all new issues are posted 
		on this list automatically.</p>
		
		<p> </p>
		<panel name="Anonymous CVS Note:">Anonymous CVS hosted by SourceForge.net has a few shorcomings.
		It is being built by synchronizing with master repository every once in a while, so there may be stale data in it.
		Also as of this writing (November 2003) anonymous CVS has been down most of the time. As an alternative 
		you may use CVS snapshots of STABLE and HEAD brances taken at 6 hour intervals and available for download
		from http://objectstyle.org/downloads/cayenne/cvs-snapshots/ .
		</panel>
        </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
