<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <body>
        <!-- Welcome section -->
        <section name="About Cayenne">
        <p>Cayenne is a powerful, full-featured OpenSource Object/Relational framework. 
        Cayenne is written in Java and is intended for Java developers working with
        relational databases. Though its current release status is Alpha, Cayenne
        has been already successfully deployed in production environment on high 
        volume sites.</p>
        
        <p>Among other things Cayenne provides management of persistent Java objects
        mapped to relational databases, single method call queries and updates 
        (including atomic updates of all modified objects), seamless integration
        of multiple databases into a single virtual data source. 
        Cayenne is distributed with CayenneModeler -
        a complete GUI mapping tool that supports reverse-engineering of RDBMS schema, 
        working with database mappings and generation of Java source code for the 
        persistent objects.</p>
        
        <p>Cayenne is an OpenSource project and as such encourages the 
        community to participate in development, testing and writing documentation.
        This way we can produce a better product that will benefit its contributors
        as well as everybody else.</p>
        </section>
        
        <!-- News section -->
        <section name="Cayenne News">
        <p><u><strong><i>December 21, 2002:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne 1.0a5 Released.</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>The main highlights of this release are: <ul>
        <li>added flattened relationships (direct many-to-many)</li>
        <li>introduced type-safe queries using Java Class as a root</li>
        <li>project structure update - linked files will have
		preset extensions. Old format can be upgraded via CayenneModeler
		and is still compatible with Cayenne runtime.</li>
        <li>bug fixes, code cleanup and refactoring</li>
        
        </ul>
         Download the release 
        	<a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">from 
        here</a>. 
        </p>
        
        
        <p><img src="images/other/nhl_logo.gif"/> 
        <u><strong><i>November 6:</i></strong> <strong>National 
        Hockey League Uses Cayenne.</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>During the playoffs, <a href="http://www.nhl.com">NHL.com</a> services 
        over a million page views per day. 
        <a href="http://objectstyle.com">ObjectStyle</a> and 
        <a href="http://www.centralparksoftware.com/">Central Park Software</a>
        teamed up to create a new player/team statistics engine based on Cayenne with JSP frontend
        and Oracle backend. The project was successfully launched in October at the beginning of 
        2002-2003 season.
        </p>
        
        </section>
        
        
        <!-- Status section -->
        <section name="History">
        <p>Idea of Cayenne was conceived back in April 2001 by a group of developers in 
        Atlanta, USA. Current version is based on that original idea and is under active 
        development since December 2001. Right now Cayenne has a growing international
        user and developer community.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
