<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <body>
        <!-- News section -->
        <section name="Cayenne News">
        <p><img src="images/other/nhl_logo.gif"/> 
        <u><strong><i>November 6:</i></strong> <strong>National 
        Hockey League Uses Cayenne.</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>During the playoffs, <a href="http://www.nhl.com">NHL.com</a> services 
        over a million page views per day. 
        <a href="http://objectstyle.com">ObjectStyle LLC</a> and 
        <a href="http://www.centralparksoftware.com/">Central Park Software</a>
        teamed up to create a new player/team statistics engine based on Cayenne with JSP frontend
        and Oracle backend. The project was successfully launched in October at the beginning of 
        2001-2002 season.
        </p>
        
        
        <p><u><strong><i>October 21:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne 1.0a4 Released.</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>The main highlights of this release are: <ul>
        <li>bug fixes, code cleanup and refactoring</li>
        <li>paginated queries</li>
        <li>serialization support of DataObjects</li>
        <li>new <a href="http://tapestry.sourceforge.net">Tapestry</a> tutorial</li>
        <li>all API deprecated in Alpha3 and earlier was removed</li>
        </ul>
         Download the release 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">from 
        here</a>. 
        </p>
        </section>
        
        <!-- Welcome section -->
        <section name="Welcome to Cayenne">
        <p>Welcome to Cayenne. Our goal is to provide Java developers with opensource 
        tools to access relational databases in an object-oriented way.</p>
        
        <p>Cayenne includes a framework that adds persistence features to Java objects.
        It allows mapping classes to database tables. Queries and updates (including 
        atomic updates of all modified objects) are done with a single method call. 
        This is a big advantage over writing SQL code in your Java program.
        Cayenne also provides GUI mapping tool (called CayenneModeler) to reverse-engineer 
        RDBMS schema and create "data maps" - XML files that contain mapping 
        between the database and Java classes. CayenneModeler can also generate 
        Java classes source code to use in your Java application.</p>
        
        
        <p>Cayenne is an opensource project and therefore encourages developer and user 
        community to participate in development, testing and writing documentation.
        This way we can produce a better product that will benefit its contributors
        as well as everybody else.</p>
        </section>
        
        <!-- Status section -->
        <section name="History">
        <p>Idea of Cayenne was conceived back in April 2001 by a group of developers in 
        Atlanta, USA. Current version is based on that original idea and is under active 
        development since December 2001. Right now Cayenne has a growing international
        user and developer community.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
