<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <body>
        <!-- News section -->
        <section name="Cayenne News">
        <p><u><strong><i>September 10:</i> Note To Cayenne Users - deprecated API removed.</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>
        API that is marked 
        	as "deprecated" in Alpha 3 release is already removed from the development code. 
        	It is no longer included in the nightly builds and will not be included with 
        	future releases. If your code uses or overrides such API, please make sure it is replaced
        	with non-deprected method calls. 
        </p>
        
        
        <p><u><strong><i>September 7:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne 
        Alpha 3 Is Out.</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>This is a maintenance release. It contains a few serious bug fixes, 
        so everybody is encouraged to upgrade. In this release:
        <ul>
        	<li>JDK1.3 port: Cayenne runtime libraries are now fully JDK1.3 compatible,
        	GUI tools still require 1.4.</li>
        	<li>Fixed a few serious problems in CayenneModeler that could potentially
        	corrupt model files.</li>
        	<li>"Derived" entities support. Derived DbEntities allow 
        	expressions in columns, including aggregate functions. They
        	also contain built in GROUP BY support.</li>
        	<li>Bugs fixes, a few convenience features and performance 
        	improvements.</li>
        	<li>Links:
        	       <ul>
        				<li><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">Download 
        				Alpha 3.</a></li>
        				<li><a href="RELEASE-NOTES-1.0a3.txt">View Release Notes.</a></li>
        			</ul>
        	</li>
        </ul>
        </p>
        
        <p><u><strong><i>July 29:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne 
        Comparison Chart.</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Having received multiple requests to compare Cayenne features
        with other O/R frameworks we decided to leverage the community collective knowledge
        to do this research. A WikiWiki page was setup to build a feature matrix at
        <a href="http://c2.com/cgi-bin/wiki?CayenneVsOther">http://c2.com/cgi-bin/wiki?CayenneVsOther</a>.
        Anybody who has experience with TopLink, CocoBase, EOF, etc. are welcome to provide
        the input interactively via WikiWiki collaboration engine. To participate, click on the link
        above, scroll to the bottom of the page and select "Edit Text".
        </p>
        </section>
        
        <!-- Welcome section -->
        <section name="Welcome to Cayenne">
        <p>Welcome to Cayenne. Our goal is to provide Java developers with opensource 
        tools to access relational databases in an object-oriented way.</p>
        
        <p>Cayenne includes a framework that adds persistence features to Java objects.
        It allows mapping classes to database tables. Queries and updates (including 
        atomic updates of all modified objects) are done with a single method call. 
        This is a big advantage over writing SQL code in your Java program.
        Cayenne also provides GUI mapping tool (called CayenneModeler) to reverse-engineer 
        RDBMS schema and create "data maps" - XML files that contain mapping 
        between the database and Java classes. CayenneModeler can also generate 
        Java classes source code to use in your Java application.</p>
        
        
        <p>Cayenne is an opensource project and therefore encourages developer and user 
        community to participate in development, testing and writing documentation.
        This way we can produce a better product that will benefit its contributors
        as well as everybody else.</p>
        </section>
        
        <!-- Status section -->
        <section name="History">
        <p>Idea of Cayenne was conceived back in April 2001 by a group of developers in 
        Atlanta, USA. Current version is based on that original idea and is under active 
        development since December 2001. Right now Cayenne has a growing international
        user and developer community.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
