<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <properties>
        <author>Andrei Adamchik</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <!-- News section -->
        <section name="Cayenne News">
        <p><i>March 18:</i> <strong><font color="red">Cayenne CVS is migrated to SourceForge.net.</font></strong> 
        Be aware that the old CVS server is no longer accessible. Go to
        <a href="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/developer.html">this page</a> for the new CVS instructions.</p>
        
        <p><i>March 16:</i> <strong>Cayenne at SourceForge and Freashmeat.</strong> Cayenne is still hosted 
        at objectstyle.org, but we also registered the project at 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/cayenne/">SourceForge.net</a>. Bug tracking, CVS and downloads 
        will be performed from SourceForge. Also Cayenne is registered at
        <a href="http://freshmeat.net/projects/cayenne/">Freshmeat.net</a> to make release announcements.</p>
        </section>
        
        <!-- Welcome section -->
        <section name="Welcome to Cayenne">
        <p>Welcome to Cayenne. Our goal is to provide Java developers with opensource 
        tools to access relational databases in an object-oriented way.</p>
        
        <p>Cayenne includes a framework that adds persistence features to Java objects.
        It allows mapping classes to database tables. Queries and updates (including 
        atomic updates of all modified objects) are done with a single method call. 
        This is a big advantage over writing SQL code in your Java program.
        Cayenne also provides GUI mapping tool (called CayenneModeler) to reverse-engineer 
        RDBMS schema and create "data maps" - XML files that contain mapping 
        between the database and Java classes. CayenneModeler can also generate 
        Java classes source code to use in your Java application.</p>
        
        
        <p>Cayenne is an opensource project and therefore encourages developer and user 
        community to participate in development, testing and writing documentation.
        This way we can produce a better product that will benefit its contributors
        as well as everybody else.</p>
        </section>
        
        <!-- Status section -->
        <section name="Status and History">
        <p>Idea of Cayenne was conceived back in April 2001 by a group of developers in Atlanta, USA. 
        Working prototype was ready
        in July. Current version is based on that prototype and is under active development 
        since December 2001. At this moment Cayenne is already a usable tool. Certain things need to
        be finished and cleaned up to make ALPHA release. But you are welcome to grab a 
        <a href="http://objectstyle.org/downloads/cayenne/nightly/">nightly 
        build</a> or a milestone release of Cayenne today.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
