<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <body>        
        <!-- News section -->
        <section name="Cayenne News">
        <p><u><strong><i>November 16, 2003:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne 1.0.3 Release</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Cayenne 1.0.3 is 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">available for 
        download</a>. It fixes numerous bugs (including a few serious ones), and adds a few new features:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Class generation via Modeler or Ant would create "public static final String" class variables
        for all class property names, and also for the column names of the entity PK.</li>
        <li>New API added to transfer objects between DataContexts.</li>
        <li>Iterator over IncrementalFaultList is now "lazy", and will resolve objects one 
        page at a time.</li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>Details can be found in the <a href="RELEASE-NOTES-1.0.3.txt">release notes</a>.
        </p>
        
        <p><u><strong><i>November 16, 2003:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne Examples 1.0.3 Release</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Cayenne Examples 1.0.3 is 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">available for 
        download</a>. It contains new aggregate queries mapping example. Examples documentation is now a part
        of the main Cayenne site. Details can be found in the <a href="RELEASE-NOTES-1.0.3.examples.txt">release notes</a>.
        </p>
        
        <p><img src="images/other/nhl_logo.gif"/> 
        <u><strong><i>May 1 2003:</i></strong> <strong>National 
        Hockey League Switches to Cayenne</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>After the initial trial of Cayenne last October, NHL
        switched all their public applications running at <a href="http://www.nhl.com">NHL.com</a>
        to use Cayenne. With the help from <a href="http://objectstyle.com">ObjectStyle</a> and 
        <a href="http://www.centralparksoftware.com/">Central Park Software</a> the site was successfully
        launched to production. Currently applications receive more than 5 million hits a day. 
        </p>
        
        <p><a href="news-archive.html"><strong>older news...</strong></a></p>
        
        </section>
        
        <!-- About section -->
        <section name="About Cayenne">
        <p>Cayenne is a powerful, full-featured OpenSource Object/Relational framework. 
        Cayenne is written in Java and is intended for Java developers working with
        relational databases. Cayenne has been successfully deployed in production environment on high 
        volume sites. Cayenne has a growing international user and developer community.</p>
        
        <p>Cayenne provides management of persistent Java objects mapped to relational databases, 
        single method call queries and updates (including atomic updates of all modified objects), 
        seamless integration of multiple databases into a single virtual data source. 
        Cayenne is distributed with CayenneModeler -
        a complete GUI mapping tool that supports reverse-engineering of RDBMS schema, 
        working with database mappings and generation of Java source code for the 
        persistent objects.</p>
        
        <p>Cayenne is an OpenSource project and as such encourages the 
        community to participate in development, testing and writing documentation.
        This way we can produce a better product that will benefit both contributors
        and user community.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
