<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <body>        
        <!-- News section -->
        <section name="Cayenne News">
        
        <p><u><i>[December 22, 2003]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne 1.0.5 Released</strong></p>
         <p>Cayenne 1.0.5 is released. It contains new Modeler Guide chapter on delete rules, improved DB2 Adapter,
         and various bug fixes. <a href="RELEASE-NOTES-1.0.5.txt">Release notes</a> contain all the details.
         Release can be downloaded from <a href="download.html">here</a>.
         </p>
         
         <p><u><i>[December 14, 2003]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne 1.0.4 Released</strong></p>
         <p>Cayenne 1.0.4 is released. It features greatly improved PostgreSQL adapter, support for large objects on
         MySQL, compound PK bug fix and other bug  fixes. Full list of changes is available in the 
         <a href="RELEASE-NOTES-1.0.4.txt">release notes</a>. 1.0.4
         can be downloaded from <a href="download.html">here</a>.
         </p>
         
         <p><u><i>[November 1, 2003]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne in "The Best Freeware And Shareware" of DB Magazine, Japan</strong></p>
         <p><img align="left" hspace="3" src="images/other/db-mag-cover-small.jpg"/> 
         A December 2003 edition of the DB Magazine, a 250-page software tecnology magazine published in Japanese, includes 
         Cayenne in the selection of "The Best Freeware &amp; Shareware". Cayenne 1.0 is also distributed on the CD that comes with the magazine.
         <br/><br/><br/><br/>
         </p>

        
        <p><u><i>[May 1 2003]</i></u> <strong>National Hockey League Switches to Cayenne</strong></p>
        
        <p><img align="left" hspace="3" src="images/other/nhl_logo.gif"/> 
        After the initial trial of Cayenne last October, NHL
        switched all their public applications running at <a href="http://www.nhl.com">NHL.com</a>
        to use Cayenne. With the help from <a href="http://objectstyle.com">ObjectStyle</a> and 
        <a href="http://www.centralparksoftware.com/">Central Park Software</a> the site was successfully
        launched to production. Currently applications receive more than 5 million hits a day. 
        <br/><br/>
        </p>
        
        <p><a href="news-archive.html"><strong>older news...</strong></a></p>
        
        </section>
        
        <!-- About section -->
        <section name="About Cayenne">
        <p>Cayenne is a powerful, full-featured OpenSource Object/Relational framework. 
        Cayenne is written in Java and is intended for Java developers working with
        relational databases. Cayenne has been successfully deployed in production environment on high 
        volume sites. Cayenne has a growing international user and developer community.</p>
        
        <p>Cayenne provides management of persistent Java objects mapped to relational databases, 
        single method call queries and updates (including atomic updates of all modified objects), 
        seamless integration of multiple databases into a single virtual data source. 
        Cayenne is distributed with CayenneModeler -
        a complete GUI mapping tool that supports reverse-engineering of RDBMS schema, 
        working with database mappings and generation of Java source code for the 
        persistent objects.</p>
        
        <p>Cayenne is an OpenSource project and as such encourages the 
        community to participate in development, testing and writing documentation.
        This way we can produce a better product that will benefit both contributors
        and user community.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
