<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Cayenne News Archive</title>

    <body>        
        <section name="Cayenne News Archive">
        <p><u><strong><i>November 16, 2003:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne 1.0.3 Release</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Cayenne 1.0.3 is 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">available for 
        download</a>. It fixes numerous bugs (including a few serious ones), and adds a few new features:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Class generation via Modeler or Ant would create "public static final String" class variables
        for all class property names, and also for the column names of the entity PK.</li>
        <li>New API added to transfer objects between DataContexts.</li>
        <li>Iterator over IncrementalFaultList is now "lazy", and will resolve objects one 
        page at a time.</li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>Details can be found in the <a href="RELEASE-NOTES-1.0.3.txt">release notes</a>.
        </p>
        
        <p><u><strong><i>November 16, 2003:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne Examples 1.0.3 Release</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Cayenne Examples 1.0.3 is 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">available for 
        download</a>. It contains new aggregate queries mapping example. Examples documentation is now a part
        of the main Cayenne site. Details can be found in the <a href="RELEASE-NOTES-1.0.3.examples.txt">release notes</a>.
        </p>
        
        <p><u><strong><i>October 27, 2003:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne 1.0.2 Maintenance Release</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Cayenne 1.0.2 is 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">available for 
        download</a>. It contains a number of adapter fixes, as well as support for binary
        primary keys. Details can be found in <a href="RELEASE-NOTES-1.0.2.txt">release notes</a>.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        <u><strong><i>July 2003:</i></strong> <strong>New Website Design</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Many thanks to our graphic artist Anna Drapeza who created this elegant site design!
        Sadly enough good artistic work is still a rare thing in the OpenSource world.
        </p>
        
        <p><img src="images/other/nhl_logo.gif"/> 
        <u><strong><i>May 1 2003:</i></strong> <strong>National 
        Hockey League Switches to Cayenne</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>After the initial trial of Cayenne last October, NHL
        switched all their public applications running at <a href="http://www.nhl.com">NHL.com</a>
        to use Cayenne. With the help from <a href="http://objectstyle.com">ObjectStyle</a> and 
        <a href="http://www.centralparksoftware.com/">Central Park Software</a> the site was successfully
        launched to production. Currently applications receive more than 5 million hits a day. 
        </p>
        
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
