<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>TODO</title>

    <properties>
        <author>Andrei Adamchik</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <!-- News section -->
        <section name="How Can I Help">
        <p>Every volunteer project gets its strength from its participants.
        We invite everybody to participate in Cayenne in any way that is suitable for you.
        
        If you are willing to help, you can do it in many different ways:
        <ul>
            <li>By contributing code for one or more tasks listsed below</li> 
            <li>By contributing documentation</li> 
            <li>By testing Cayenne and reporting bugs</li>
            <li>By using Cayenne and reporting bugs</li>
            <li>By suggesting your own ideas on the mailing list</li>
        </ul>        
        </p>
        
        <p>If you want to become a contributor, first you should probably subscribe to 
        <a href="http://objectstyle.org/developer/mailinglists.html">Cayenne Developer Mailing List.</a>
        to see what issues are discussed and to communicate with the project team.</p>
        
        <p>Normally code and documentation contributions are made via patches sent
        to developer list. 
        A good discussion on how to create and submit code patches is located at 
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/source.html">Jakarta Apache</a> site.
        You can use all these hints as related to Cayenne.
        </p>
        </section>
 
        <!-- Tasks section -->
        <section name="Tasks">
            <subsection name="Top Priority">
                <p><strong>Cayenne Modeler GUI.</strong> Currently in progress.</p>
                <p><strong>Stored Procedure Support</strong></p>
                <p><strong>Test with Oracle.</strong> Make sure test cases pass</p>
                <p><strong>Test with PostgreSQL.</strong> Make sure test cases pass.</p>
                <p><strong>Add "revert" function to DataContext</strong></p>
                <p><strong>Test numeric types handling</strong></p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Medium Priority">
                <p><strong>Allow SelectQuery to hold arbitrary attributes beyond 
                ObjEntity attributes set.</strong> Right now only SqlSelectQuery has 
                this feature, must add it to SelectQuery as well.</p>
                
                <p><strong>Add prefetching support to queries.</strong></p>
                
                <p><strong>Performance testing/optimization.</strong></p>
                
                <p><strong>Blob/Clob support</strong></p>
                
                <p><strong>Mapping of query qualifier parameters to DbAttributes (or maybe database 
                types).</strong></p>

                <p><strong>SQL schemas support in test cases.</strong></p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Lower Priority">
           <p><strong>Test with other database engines</strong> Current implementation should support
           Oracle, Sybase, MySQL and PostgreSQL. We need to write database adapters for other engines as well
            </p>
            
            <p><strong>Application server integration.</strong> Cayenne has basic JNDI support. 
            We are running with Jakarta-Tomcat container. Research on how to use Cayenne with other containers
            like WebLogic, WebSphere, etc. still needs to be done.
            </p>

            <p><strong>"To Many" relationship Ordering.</strong> Users should be able to specify 
            "to many" relationship ordering in the map. 
            In current release objects will be returned in a database "natural" order.
            </p>

            <p><strong>Flattened relationships.</strong> Though current API "supports" mapping 
            of ObjRelationship across multiple DbRelationships, it doesn't really work. 
            Real support still needs to be built in Cayenne.
            </p>

            <p><strong>Selecting attributes for optimistic locking.</strong> 
            DataMap should support arbitrary attributes in "optimistic" locking. 
            Now only primary key attributes are used.</p>
            
            <p><strong>Subquery support</strong></p>
            
            <p><strong>Union query support</strong></p>
            
            <p><strong>Aggregate functions and "group by"/"having" support</strong></p>
            
            <p><strong>Cascading delete rules</strong></p>
            </subsection>
        
        
       
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
