<document>
<title>User Guide - Introduction</title>
<body>
    <section name="1. Introduction" toc="/userguide/index.html">
    
		<subsection name="1.1 About Cayenne" anchor="about">
            <p>Cayenne is a free Java object-relational (O/R) persistence framework.
            Its goal is to provide Java developers with commercial quality opensource
            tools to work with relational databases in an object-oriented way.
           </p>

            <p>Usually, a persistence framework creates
            an interface from your program to the relational database. Such interfaces
            make database access more "transparent", since it is based on object concepts 
            rather than thinly wrapped SQL. Cayenne provides this and more. First,
            "transparent" does not mean that you can't do what you used to do with SQL. 
            You still can. Also Cayenne includes GUI tool to automate and streamline most 
            mapping tasks. Cayenne allows tying multiple database
			into what looks to the application like a single data source. Cayenne
			allows issuing a direct SQL query, calling stored procedures, setting
			the automatic primary key generation, caching policy, integrating
			with EJB-s, and other things. Some of the ideas used in Cayenne
			have been inspired by the persistence mechanism of NeXT' (and now
			Apple's) WebObjects application server.
            </p>
            
            <p>Cayenne may help to reduce the development time in any project with
			the frequently changed business requirements and as a result
			database structure; it is very useful in the projects where data
			comes from the multiple databases. Even if the database structure
			doesn't change frequently, it will help to reduce the development time
			for writing data retrieval and saving logic.
            </p>
            
            <p>Cayenne is the tool created by the programmer community for the
			programmer community. Though it will eventually be a very easy tool
			to use, it is not an easy tool to create. If you can think of the feature,
			which would improve it, please let us know - we will be glad to
			incorporate it in the future versions. But if you are a seasoned
			programmer willing to commit your time and energy for something
			which will benefit thousands of people, we will be particularly glad to
			hear from you.
            </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="1.2 Contributors" anchor="contrib">
            <p>Latest list of contributors is located <a href="../contributors.html">here</a>.</p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="1.3 License" anchor="license">
            <p>This software is distributed and should be used on terms of Apache software license. 
            In short, it is free of charge, and unrestricted for commercial use as well. Full license text
            can be found <a href="../LICENSE">here</a>.</p>
        </subsection>
    </section>
</body>
</document>
