<document>
<title>User Guide - Design</title>
<navigator>
	<up>/userguide/index.html</up>
	<prev>/userguide/quickstart/index.html</prev>
	<next>/userguide/design/dataobj.html</next>
</navigator>
<body>
    <section name="3. Design">
        <subsection name="3.1 Object Relational Mapping" anchor="or_map">
            <p>Normally mapping is done between Java class and a database table. This 
            way instance of such class (an object) will map to a single database row.
            Some properties of such object (properties in a "JavaBeans" sense) would map 
            to table columns. For example String, and numeric properties. Other properties
            would map to database primary-foreign key relationships. Summarizing possible 
            mappings we have the following correspondence:</p>
            
            <ul>
                <li>Java class -&gt; database table</li>
                <li>"simple" class property -&gt; table column</li>
                <li>"complex" class property -&gt; related table via a database relationship</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
                <li>Java object -&gt; row in a table</li>
                <li>"simple" object property value -&gt; value of column in a row</li>
                <li>"complex" object property value -&gt; another object or list of objects</li>
            </ul>
        
            <p>This way O/R 
            framework allows programmer to get access to an "object tree" - objects 
            interconnected via relationship properties. Object tree is a view of a subset
            of database data and relationships between this data - all without 
            the need to write SQL code in Java applications. The most important
            property of the object tree is its ability to be synchronized with the database.
            This works both ways - object tree can get updated when the database data has changed
            or database will be updated when an object tree was changed by the Java application.</p>
            
            <p>The above statement doesn't mean that Caynne would automatically poll the database for 
            the updated data, or automatically save the data. This would have killed the performance 
            of the application and made it unpredictable. Instead Java application is always in full 
            control of these operations.</p>            
        </subsection>
    </section>
</body>
</document>
