<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Bugs and Features</title>

    <body>        
        <!-- News section -->
        <section name="Issue Tracking">
      	
      	<p>Cayenne utilizes an advanced issue tracker that maintains a database of bugs, feature requests and improvements,
      	allowing collaborative project management and more. It is based on JIRA software from atlassian.com. Below are a few 
      	quick links to the important sections of the issue tracker:
		</p>
		
      	<ul>
      		<li><a href="http://objectstyle.org/jira/secure/CreateIssue!default.jspa">Submit New Bug or Feature Request</a></li>
      		<li><a href="http://objectstyle.org/jira/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10000">Browse All Issues</a></li>
      		<li><a href="http://objectstyle.org/jira/secure/Signup!default.jspa">Register to Submit and Track Issues</a></li>
      	</ul>

		<subsection name="JIRA Tips">
		<ul>			
			<li><strong>Who Should Register?</strong> Users are allowed to browse the database of Cayenne issues without 
			logging in. But in order to submit, track, and vote on issues a user must register with JIRA.  Use the 
			"Register.." link above to create an account.
			<br/><br/></li>
			
			<li><strong>When I submit a Bug, Do I Also Need to Notify cayenne-devel List?</strong> No, JIRA will post all new issues to cayenne-devel
			mailing list automatically.
			<br/><br/></li>
			
			<li><strong>How Do I receive Email Updates When an Issue Changes?</strong> If you are a reporter or an assignee of
			the issue, e-mail updates will be sent automatically whenever the issue is modified. If you are not one of these people,
			you can use the "watch" feature. You must have a valid JIRA account, log in, select an issue and click on "Watch It" link on the left.
			<br/><br/></li>
			
			<li><strong>How Do I Indicate That an Issue Is Important to Me?</strong> JIRA has a "vote"
			feature. You must have a valid JIRA account, log in, select an issue and click on "Vote For It" link on the left. Cayenne team
			will take popularity votes into consideration, but makes no guarantees as to when and if a particular feature will become a 
			part of Cayenne.
			<br/><br/></li>
		</ul>
		</subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
