<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <body>        
         <section name="Cayenne: Professional Object Relational Mapping">
        <p>Cayenne is a powerful, full-featured Java Object Relational Mapping framework. It is open source
        and completely free. One of the main Cayenne distinctions is that it comes with cross-platform 
        modeling GUI tools. This places Cayenne in the league of its own, making it a very attractive
        choice over both closed source commerical products and traditional "edit your own XML" open 
        source solutions.
        </p>
        </section>
        
        <section name="Project News">
        
		<p><u><i>[April 25, 2004]</i></u> <strong>M6 - Cayenne 1.1 Milestone  Release</strong></p>
		<p>This release includes SQLTemplate, a scriptable raw SQL query, and also a number of 
		bug fixes and other enhancements. For details see <a href="release-notes/RELEASE-NOTES-1.1M6.txt">release
		notes</a> and <a href="upgrade/UPGRADE-1.1M6.txt">upgrade instructions</a>.
		</p>
         
        <p><u><i>[April 14, 2004]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne Success Story - AccessPoint Inc.</strong></p>
		<p>A story submitted by Bret Gregory: "I work for <a href="http://www.accesspointinc.com/" target="_new">AccessPoint 
         Inc.</a>, a privately-held CLEC offering 
        integrated communications services to small- and medium-sized businesses.  We use Cayenne for 
        our internal accounting and reconciliation application.  This application allows us to recognize 
        uncaptured revenue streams as well as accounting margins and billing errors.  In addition, Cayenne 
        is used in our internal reporting application.  These applications and thus Cayenne are central to the 
        financial health of the company." </p>
        
        <p><a href="poweredby.html">More success stories...</a>
         </p>
        
         <p><u><i>[April 14, 2004]</i></u> <strong>M5 - Cayenne 1.1 Milestone  Release</strong></p>
         <p>This release includes two major new features - optimistic locking and entity inheritance, and also
         a number of bug fixes and other enhancements. For details see <a href=
         "release-notes/RELEASE-NOTES-1.1M5.txt">release notes</a> and 
         <a href="upgrade/UPGRADE-1.1M5.txt">upgrade instructions</a>.
         </p>
         
         <p><u><i>[November 1, 2003]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne in "The Best Freeware And Shareware" of DB Magazine, Japan</strong></p>
         <p><img align="left" hspace="3" src="images/other/db-mag-cover-small.jpg"/> 
         A December 2003 edition of the DB Magazine, a 250-page software tecnology magazine published in Japanese, includes 
         Cayenne in the selection of "The Best Freeware &amp; Shareware". Cayenne 1.0 is also distributed on the CD that comes with the magazine.
         <br/><br/><br/><br/>
         </p>

        <p><u><i>[May 1 2003]</i></u> <strong>National Hockey League Switches to Cayenne</strong></p>
        
        <p><img align="left" hspace="3" src="images/other/nhl_logo.gif"/> 
        After the initial trial of Cayenne last October, NHL
        switched all their public applications running at <a href="http://www.nhl.com">NHL.com</a>
        to use Cayenne. With the help from <a href="http://objectstyle.com">ObjectStyle</a> and 
        <a href="http://www.centralparksoftware.com/">Central Park Software</a> the site was successfully
        launched to production. Currently applications receive more than 5 million hits a day. 
        <br/><br/>
        </p>
        
        <p><a href="news-archive.html"><strong>older news...</strong></a></p>
        
        </section>
        
        <section name="About Cayenne">
        <p>Cayenne provides management of persistent Java objects mapped to relational databases, 
        single method call queries and updates (including atomic updates of all modified objects), 
        seamless integration of multiple databases into a single virtual data source. 
        Cayenne is distributed with CayenneModeler - a complete GUI mapping tool that supports 
        reverse-engineering of RDBMS schema, working with database mappings and generation of 
        Java source code for the persistent objects. Cayenne has been successfully deployed in 
        production environment on high volume sites and has a constantly growing international community.</p>
        
        <p>Cayenne is an open source project and we encourage the 
        community to participate in development, testing and writing documentation.
        This way we can produce a better product that will benefit both contributors
        and user community.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
