<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <body>        
         <section name="Cayenne: Professional Object Relational Mapping">
        <p>Cayenne is a powerful, full-featured Java Object Relational Mapping framework. It is open source
        and completely free. One of the main Cayenne distinctions is that it comes with cross-platform 
        modeling GUI tools. This places Cayenne in the league of its own, making it a very attractive
        choice over both closed source commercial products and traditional "edit your own XML" open 
        source solutions.
        </p>
        </section>
        

        <section name="Project News">
<p><u><i>[March 20, 2005]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne 1.2M3 Released</strong></p>
		<p>A new M3 milestone release of Cayenne 1.2 is available. It includes a number of new features, improvements and 
		bug fixes. The most notable changes are support for single query ("joint") prefetching, support for flattened relationships 
		prefetching, PostgreSQL PK generator using sequences instead of AUTO_PK_SUPPORT table, DataContext userProperties 
		map. For more details see the 
		<a href="http://objectstyle.org/confluence/display/CAY/2005/03/20/Cayenne+1.2M3+Released">release announcement</a>
		 on Cayenne Blog.</p>
<p><u><i>[March 13, 2005]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne 1.1.1 Released</strong></p>
		<p>A new maintenance release of Cayenne stable 1.1 version is now available. It fixes a number of bugs (such as Oracle resource leaks, modeler not escaping strings, etc.). For a full list of resolved issues see this 
		<a href="http://objectstyle.org/confluence/display/CAY/2005/03/13/Cayenne+1.1.1+Released">blog entry</a>
		 or release notes file included with download.</p>

           

        <p><u><i>[Aug 30, 2004]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne on the Cover of JavaWorld Japan</strong></p>
		<p><img align="left" hspace="3" src="images/other/javaworld-200409.gif"/>
		Cayenne sure gets some press coverage in Japan lately. A September edition of JavaWorld Japan has 
		a big article on Cayenne, including a sample Tapestry application
		(pp. 94-112, Cayenne 1.0.7 is used). Big thanks to Manabu Yoneyama for sending me a copy of the magazine.
		<br/><br/><br/><br/></p>
		

		<p><u><i>[June 12, 2004]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne vs. Hibernate</strong></p>
		<p>Bill Dudney posted a <a target="_blank"  href="http://www.theserverside.com/blogs/showblog.tss?id=CayenneAndHibernate">Cayenne 
		vs. Hibernate</a> entry in his blog. This ended up as a <a target="_blank"  href="http://www.theserverside.com/news/thread.tss?thread_id=26498">pretty 
		long thread</a>  discussing the merits of GUI tools for ORM among other things.
		</p>
		
        <p><u><i>[June 2, 2004]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne Article on TheServerSide.com</strong></p>
		<p><img align="left" width="73" height="45" hspace="3" src="images/other/cayenne_tss.gif"/>  TheServerSide.com <a target="_blank" href="http://theserverside.com/articles/article.tss?l=Cayenne">published 
		an article</a>  by Andrus Adamchik and Eric Schneider introducing
		Cayenne and its productivity tools.  Discuss this article on <a target="_blank" 
		href="http://theserverside.com/news/thread.tss?thread_id=26325">TheServerSide forum</a>.
		<br/><br/><br/><br/></p>
		
        <p><u><i>[May 1 2003]</i></u> <strong>National Hockey League Switches to Cayenne</strong></p>
        
        <p><img align="left" hspace="3" src="images/other/nhl_logo.gif"/> 
        After the initial trial of Cayenne last October, NHL
        switched all their public applications running at <a href="http://www.nhl.com">NHL.com</a>
        to use Cayenne. With the help from <a href="http://objectstyle.com">ObjectStyle</a> and 
        <a href="http://www.centralparksoftware.com/">Central Park Software</a> the site was successfully
        launched to production. Currently applications receive more than 5 million hits a day. 
        <br/><br/>
        </p>
<p> </p>
        
        <p><a href="http://objectstyle.org/confluence/pages/viewrecentblogposts.action?key=CAY"><strong>other news...</strong></a> <a href="http://objectstyle.org/confluence/display/CAY/Old+News+Archive"><strong>old news...</strong></a></p>
        
        </section>
        
        <section name="About Cayenne">
        <p>Cayenne provides management of persistent Java objects mapped to relational databases, 
        single method call queries and updates (including atomic updates of all modified objects), 
        seamless integration of multiple databases into a single virtual data source. 
        Cayenne is distributed with CayenneModeler - a complete GUI mapping tool that supports 
        reverse-engineering of RDBMS schema, working with database mappings and generation of 
        Java source code for the persistent objects. Cayenne has been successfully deployed in 
        production environment on high volume sites and has a constantly growing international community.</p>
        
        <p>Cayenne is an open source project and we encourage the 
        community to participate in development, testing and writing documentation.
        This way we can produce a better product that will benefit both contributors
        and user community.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
