<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Cayenne News Archive</title>

    <body>        
        <section name="Cayenne News Archive">
        
        <p><u><i>[June 14, 2004]</i></u> <strong>M7 - Cayenne 1.1 Milestone  Release</strong></p>
		<p>This release includes support for shared and local caching of query results, a complete
		GUI support for all types of queries, and also lots of bug fixes.. For details see 
		<a href="release-notes/RELEASE-NOTES-1.1M7.txt">release
		notes</a> and <a href="upgrade/UPGRADE-1.1M7.txt">upgrade instructions</a>.
		</p>
		<p><strong>M7 Note:</strong> There was a bug discovered in M7 that prevents JavaGroups 
		remote notifications from happenning. If you are using JavaGroups notifications feature please
		<a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/cayenne/cayenne-1.1M7_1.tar.gz">upgrade 
		to M7_1</a>. Otherwise M7 should work just fine.</p>
		
		
		<p><u><i>[April 25, 2004]</i></u> <strong>M6 - Cayenne 1.1 Milestone  Release</strong></p>
		<p>This release includes SQLTemplate, a scriptable raw SQL query, and also a number of 
		bug fixes and other enhancements. For details see <a href="release-notes/RELEASE-NOTES-1.1M6.txt">release
		notes</a> and <a href="upgrade/UPGRADE-1.1M6.txt">upgrade instructions</a>.
		</p>
		
         <p><u><i>[April 14, 2004]</i></u> <strong>M5 - Cayenne 1.1 Milestone  Release</strong></p>
         <p>This release includes two major new features - optimistic locking and entity inheritance, and also
         a number of bug fixes and other enhancements. For details see <a href=
         "release-notes/RELEASE-NOTES-1.1M5.txt">release notes</a> and 
         <a href="upgrade/UPGRADE-1.1M5.txt">upgrade instructions</a>.
         </p>
         
		<p><u><i>[March 4, 2004]</i></u> <strong>M4 - New Cayenne 1.1 Milestone  Release</strong></p>
         <p>This release fixes serious bugs found in M3, adds suppport for to-one relationships with an FK column
         target and implements performance enhancements for to-many relationships.
         </p>
         
         <p><u><strong><i>February 29, 2004</i></strong></u> <strong>M3 - New Cayenne 1.1 Milestone  Release</strong></p>
         <p>This release features major enhancement of Expressions API and allows to build SelectQueries using CayenneModeler.
         </p>
         
         <p><u><strong><i>February 8, 2004</i></strong></u> <strong>Release 1.1a-pre2 of Cayenne and Cayenne Examples</strong></p>
         <p>Cayenne and Cayenne Examples 1.1a-pre2 (Second Alpha Preview) are released. This release features 
         1.1 release. Among its features are:
         <ul>
         <li>Modeler and API support for container-managed transactions</li>
         <li>Cayenne with SessionBean facade JBoss example</li>
         <li>"Import DataMap" function in CayenneModeler</li>
         <li>MS SQL Server Adapter</li>
         <li>various bug fixes</li>
         </ul>
         </p>
        
        <p><u><i>[January 26, 2004]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne 1.0.6 Released</strong></p>
         <p>Cayenne 1.0.6 is released. It contains extended implementation of in-memory Expressions
         evaluation and numerous bug fixes.
         </p>
         
        <p><u><strong><i>November 16, 2003:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne 1.0.3 Release</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Cayenne 1.0.3 is 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">available for 
        download</a>. It fixes numerous bugs (including a few serious ones), and adds a few new features:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Class generation via Modeler or Ant would create "public static final String" class variables
        for all class property names, and also for the column names of the entity PK.</li>
        <li>New API added to transfer objects between DataContexts.</li>
        <li>Iterator over IncrementalFaultList is now "lazy", and will resolve objects one 
        page at a time.</li>
        </ul>
        
        <p><u><strong><i>November 16, 2003:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne Examples 1.0.3 Release</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Cayenne Examples 1.0.3 is 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">available for 
        download</a>. It contains new aggregate queries mapping example. Examples documentation is now a part
        of the main Cayenne site.
        </p>
        
          <p><u><i>[November 1, 2003]</i></u> <strong>Cayenne in "The Best Freeware And Shareware" of DB Magazine, Japan</strong></p>
         <p><img align="left" hspace="3" src="images/other/db-mag-cover-small.jpg"/> 
         A December 2003 edition of the DB Magazine, a 250-page software tecnology magazine published in Japanese, includes 
         Cayenne in the selection of "The Best Freeware &amp; Shareware". Cayenne 1.0 is also distributed on the CD that comes with the magazine.
         <br/><br/><br/><br/>
         </p>
        
        
        <p><u><strong><i>October 27, 2003:</i></strong> <strong>Cayenne 1.0.2 Maintenance Release</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Cayenne 1.0.2 is 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=48132">available for 
        download</a>. It contains a number of adapter fixes, as well as support for binary
        primary keys.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        <u><strong><i>July 2003:</i></strong> <strong>New Website Design</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>Many thanks to our graphic artist Anna Drapeza who created this elegant site design!
        Sadly enough good artistic work is still a rare thing in the OpenSource world.
        </p>
        
        <p><img src="images/other/nhl_logo.gif"/> 
        <u><strong><i>May 1 2003:</i></strong> <strong>National 
        Hockey League Switches to Cayenne</strong></u></p>
        
        <p>After the initial trial of Cayenne last October, NHL
        switched all their public applications running at <a href="http://www.nhl.com">NHL.com</a>
        to use Cayenne. With the help from <a href="http://objectstyle.com">ObjectStyle</a> and 
        <a href="http://www.centralparksoftware.com/">Central Park Software</a> the site was successfully
        launched to production. Currently applications receive more than 5 million hits a day. 
        </p>
        
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
