<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<title>Powered By Cayenne</title>
	<properties>
		<author>Andrei Adamchik</author>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Success Stories">
			<p><strong>National Hockey League</strong> (<a target="_new"
				href="http://www.nhl.com/">http://www.nhl.com/</a>)</p>
			<p>After the initial trial of Cayenne in October 2002, NHL switched 
				all their public applications running at <a target="_new" 
				href="http://www.nhl.com">NHL.com</a> to use Cayenne. With help 
				from <a target="_new" 
				href="http://objectstyle.com">ObjectStyle</a> and <a 
				target="_new" 
				href="http://www.centralparksoftware.com/">Central Park 
				Software</a> the site was successfully launched to production. 
				Currently applications receive more than 5 million hits a day. 
				</p>
			<p><strong>Global Legal Information Network (GLIN)</strong> (<a target="_new" 
				href="http://www.glin.gov/">http://www.glin.gov/</a>)</p>
			<p>GLIN is a legal repository for the Law Library
			of Congress. It has been around for 30 years, and in digital
			form since the early 90s. However, it was only partially publicly
			available before February 2005 when a Cayenne-based system was launched.
			The system has roughly 200,000 records, spanning 200 gb of fulltext data
			and 15 gb of associated metadata. It represents
			the world's largest publicly available legal index, spanning 10
			languages and 35 jurisdictions. The system is accessible in 4
			languages currently and will support 14 languages in the nearest future, thus becoming 
			the most internationalized site in the federal government, after the IRS.
			</p>

			<p><strong>RossoAlice</strong> (<a target="_new" 
				href="http://www.rossoalice.it/">http://www.rossoalice.it/</a>)</p>
			<p>
			RossoAlice is an Italian media portal. This is a site where users can download music, watch films,  
			download games, watch television news and more. The java database layer for the 
			authentication / authorization  component is developed with Cayenne.
			</p>

			<p><strong>Pixxures Inc.</strong> (<a target="_new" 
				href="http://www.pixxures.ca/">http://www.pixxures.ca/</a>)</p>
			<p><a target="_new" href="http://www.pixxures.ca/">Pixxures 
				Inc.</a> is the world's largest provider of digital mapping 
				products, services, and online delivery capabilities. Pixxures 
				used Cayenne to create a private website for a client that 
				sells satellite images for crop analysis to the agriculture 
				industry. The site contains ordering and image production 
				system. Now Pixxures plans to revamp their main software to use 
				Cayenne instead of the connection pooling system and the other 
				data access methods. </p>
			<p><strong>AccessPoint Inc.</strong> (<a 
				href="http://www.accesspointinc.com/" 
				target="_new">http://www.accesspointinc.com/</a>)</p>
			<p>A story submitted by Bret Gregory: "I work for AccessPoint Inc., 
				a privately-held CLEC offering integrated communications 
				services to small- and medium-sized businesses. We use Cayenne 
				for our internal accounting and reconciliation application. 
				This application allows us to recognize uncaptured revenue 
				streams as well as accounting margins and billing errors. In 
				addition, Cayenne is used in our internal reporting 
				application. These applications and thus Cayenne are central to 
				the financial health of the company." </p>
			<p><strong>ObjectVisualizer Inc.</strong> (<a 
				href="http://www.objectvisualizer.com/" 
				target="_new">http://www.objectvisualizer.com/</a>)</p>
			<p>ObjectVisualizer is a business intelligence tool that builds 
				upon Object Persistence technology to provide easy to use 
				query, reporting, and charting capabilities. Features include: 
				Query and filter data using objects, Interactive Data Table, 
				Report Generation, Chart Creation, and Plugin Architecture. 
				ObjectVisualizer has a Cayenne plugin to work with Cayenne 
				mapping projects.</p>
			<p></p>
			<panel name="Powered by Cayenne">If your site or project uses 
				Cayenne as its Object-Relational engine, please drop a note to 
				cayenne-user list or directly to "andrus at objectstyle.org". 
				Provided information will be displayed on this page. </panel>
		</section>
		<section name="Cayenne Badges">
			<p>Also we developed a few web badges to enable you to endorse 
				Cayenne technology. Help us to spread the word and promote 
				Cayenne. If your site or project uses Cayenne, you may put one 
				of the following badges on the site. Badge should be configured 
				as an active link to Cayenne website: 
				http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/ </p>
			<p>
				<img src="images/powered-by-cayenne-green1.gif" width="170" 
					height="45"/>
			</p>
			<p> &lt;a href="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/"&gt;&lt;img 
				src="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/images/powered-by-cayenne-green1.gif" 
				width="170" height="45" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; </p>
			<p>
				<img src="images/powered-by-cayenne-green2.gif" width="170" 
					height="45"/>
			</p>
			<p> &lt;a href="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/"&gt;&lt;img 
				src="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/images/powered-by-cayenne-green2.gif" 
				width="170" height="45" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; </p>
			<p>
				<img src="images/powered-by-cayenne-white.gif" width="170" 
					height="45"/>
			</p>
			<p> &lt;a href="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/"&gt;&lt;img 
				src="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/images/powered-by-cayenne-white.gif" 
				width="170" height="45" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; </p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>