<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <title>Powered By Cayenne</title>

    <properties>
        <author>Andrei Adamchik</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Success Stories">
        <p><strong>National Hockey League</strong> 
        (<a target="_new" href="http://www.nhl.com/">http://www.nhl.com/</a>)</p>
        
        <p>After the initial trial of Cayenne in October 2002, NHL
        switched all their public applications running at <a target="_new" href="http://www.nhl.com">NHL.com</a>
        to use Cayenne. With help from <a target="_new" href="http://objectstyle.com">ObjectStyle</a> and 
        <a target="_new" href="http://www.centralparksoftware.com/">Central Park Software</a> the site was successfully
        launched to production. Currently applications receive more than 5 million hits a day. 
        </p>
        
        <p><strong>Pixxures Inc.</strong> 
        (<a target="_new" href="http://www.pixxures.ca/">http://www.pixxures.ca/</a>)</p>
        
        <p><a target="_new" href="http://www.pixxures.ca/">Pixxures Inc.</a> is the world's largest provider of 
        digital mapping products, services, and online delivery capabilities. 
        Pixxures used Cayenne to create a private website for a client that sells satellite images for 
        crop analysis to the agriculture industry. The site contains ordering and image production system. 
        Now Pixxures plans to revamp their main software to use Cayenne instead of the connection 
        pooling system and the other data access methods.
        </p>
        
		<p><strong>AccessPoint Inc.</strong> 
        (<a href="http://www.accesspointinc.com/" target="_new">http://www.accesspointinc.com/</a>)</p>
        
        <p>A story submitted by Bret Gregory: "I work for AccessPoint Inc., a privately-held CLEC offering 
        integrated communications services to small- and medium-sized businesses.  We use Cayenne for 
        our internal accounting and reconciliation application.  This application allows us to recognize 
        uncaptured revenue streams as well as accounting margins and billing errors.  In addition, Cayenne 
        is used in our internal reporting application.  These applications and thus Cayenne are central to the 
        financial health of the company."
        </p>
        
        <p></p>
        <panel name="Powered by Cayenne">If your site or project uses Cayenne as its Object-Relational engine, 
        please drop a note to cayenne-user list or directly to "andrus at objectstyle.org". 
        Provided information will be displayed on this page.
        </panel>
        
     </section>
     
    <section name="Cayenne Badges">
        <p>Also we developed a few web badges to enable you to endorse Cayenne technology.
        Help us to spread the word and promote Cayenne. If your site or project uses
        Cayenne, you may put one of the following badges on the site. Badge should be configured
        as an active link to Cayenne website: http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/
        </p>
        
        <p><img src="images/powered-by-cayenne-green1.gif" width="170" height="45"/></p>
        <p>
		&lt;a href="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/"&gt;&lt;img 
			src="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/images/powered-by-cayenne-green1.gif" 
			width="170" 
			height="45" 
			border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
		</p>
		<p>
			<img src="images/powered-by-cayenne-green2.gif" width="170" height="45"/>
		</p>
		  <p>
		&lt;a href="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/"&gt;&lt;img 
			src="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/images/powered-by-cayenne-green2.gif" 
			width="170" 
			height="45" 
			border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
		</p>
		
		<p>
			<img src="images/powered-by-cayenne-white.gif" width="170" height="45"/>
        </p>
          <p>
		&lt;a href="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/"&gt;&lt;img 
			src="http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/images/powered-by-cayenne-white.gif" 
			width="170" 
			height="45" 
			border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
		</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
