<document>
<title>User Guide - Installation</title>

<navigator>
	<up>/userguide/index.html</up>
	<prev>/userguide/intro.html</prev>
	<next>/userguide/quickstart/index.html</next>
</navigator>

<body>
    <section name="2. Installation">
        <subsection name="2.1 System Requirements" anchor="sys_req">
            <p>Cayenne, including GUI tools, is written in 100% Java,
            and therefore should run out of the box on any Java-compatible platform. 
            More detailed requirements are listed below:</p>
            
            <p><strong>- JSDK 1.4 :</strong> Cayenne requires JSDK 1.4 or newer and will not
            run with earlier versions. To download it from Sun go to <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/">
            http://java.sun.com/products/</a> or directly to <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/index.html">
            http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/index.html</a></p>		
                
            <p><strong>- Operating System compatible with JSDK 1.4 :</strong> Currently this is
            Linux, Solaris and Windows 95 / 98 / ME / 2000 / NT 4.0. MacOS support should be coming soon.</p>
                
            <p><strong>- Access to a relational database and JDBC driver for 
            this database :</strong> Out of the box, Cayenne would 
            support Oracle, Sybase, MySQL and PostgreSQL databases. 
            Certain level of support exists for any other database that has a 
            JDBC driver available but this is untested and not guaranteed. List of
            available JDBC drivers can be found at 
            <a href="http://industry.java.sun.com/products/jdbc/drivers">
            http://industry.java.sun.com/products/jdbc/drivers</a>.
            <i>Note that to run Cayenne unit tests you will need "CREATE TABLE" and 
            "DROP TABLE" database privileges since tests supplied with 
            Cayenne will create all the tables on the fly.</i>
            </p>
            
            <p><strong>- (Optional) Ant 1.4.1 :</strong> Users who downloaded source or binary 
            distribution WILL NOT need Ant. Only if you plan to <a href="#compile">build it yourself</a>
			(you don't have to!), you will need Ant. Version 1.4.1 or newer is required,
			older versions will not work. Ant can be downloaded from
            <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/index.html">http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/index.html</a>.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="2.2 Installation" anchor="inst">
            <p>This section describes the steps needed to install Cayenne source or 
            binary distribution.</p>
            
            <p>Download Cayenne from <a href=
            "http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/download.html">
            http://objectstyle.org/cayenne/download.html</a>. 
            Choose the type of download that fits your needs. If you need
            a stable version, download source or binary <strong>release</strong>.
            To get the latest features, download source or binary <strong>nightly
            build</strong> (of course when using nightly builds users run into the risks 
            accociated with running development code). Downloaded file is called 
            something like <code>cayenne-[release-suffix].tar.gz</code>.
            </p>
            
            <p>Unpack <code>cayenne-[release-suffix].tar.gz</code> into the target installation
            directory. On Windows you can use <a href=
            "http://www.winzip.com/">WinZip</a> to unpack the distribution. 
            WinZip supports UNIX .tar.gz archives, therefore Cayenne is not provided as a zip file. 
            On UNIX, run the following command:</p>
            
            <source># gz -dc [filename].tar.gz | tar xf -</source>
                
            <p>or if you happen to have GNU tar</p>
                
            <source># tar xzf [filename].tar.gz</source>
            
            <p>To take advantage of the scripts located in the <code>bin</code>
            directory of Cayenne, set the following environment variables:
            <ul>
                <li><code>CAYENNE_HOME</code> - should point to
                the directory created when your unpacked Cayenne distribution in the previous 
                steps. (Directory named like <code>cayenne-[release-suffix]</code>). </li>
                    
                <li><code>JAVA_HOME</code> - should point to your JSDK 1.4 installation. 
                It may already exist in the environment.</li>
            </ul>
            
            <i>Note that these variables are only necessary to use the scripts
            that run unit tests and start CayenneModeler. 
            They are probably not needed on a deployment machine.</i>
            </p>
            
            <p>Installation is complete.</p>
        </subsection>
        
        
        <subsection name="2.3 Cayenne JAR Files" anchor="jar">
            <p>There are two JAR files in <code>[cayenne_install_dir]/lib</code>
            directory: <code>cayenne.jar</code> and <code>cayenne-nodeps.jar</code>. 
            Either one or another should be used (<strong>but not both of them</strong>
            at the same time).
            In most cases <code>cayenne.jar</code> is the best choice. It has 
            Cayenne classes as well as all the needed dependencies. 
            Dependencies include <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/">Velocity 
            Template Engine</a> classes, and are bundled with Cayenne for simpler installation 
            and configuration. A leaner <code>cayenne-nodeps.jar</code> file
            should only be used if Velocity is already installed on the user machine
            or a user wants to install it herself. 
            <i>Note that Cayenne was tested with Velocity version 1.3. 
            There is no guarantee that it will work with other versions.</i>
            </p>
            
            <p>Make sure that <code>[cayenne_install_dir]/lib/cayenne.jar</code> is accessible by 
			the 
            applications that use Cayenne. This can be done in many different ways depending on
            what you are planning to use Cayenne for. The simplest way is to copy
            <code>cayenne.jar</code> (or <code>cayenne-nodeps.jar</code> 
            to your JRE extensions directory 
            ($JRE_HOME/lib/ext or $JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/ext).</p>
        </subsection>
        
        
        <subsection name="2.4 Unit Tests" anchor="tests">        
            <p>[Optional] Run tests. To do that, you will need to set CAYENNE_HOME and 
            JAVA_HOME environment variables as described <a href="#inst">above</a>. When 
            this is 
            done, you can run test start script. On Windows, from the command line run:</p>
            
            <source>%CAYENNE_HOME%\bin\runtests.bat</source>
                
            <p>On UNIX, run:</p>
			
            <source>$CAYENNE_HOME/bin/runtests.sh</source>
                
			<p>Test runner will present a graphic login panel that has some canned settings for
			supported databases (use dropdown in the upper right corner):</p>
			<img src="/images/ulogin.gif" width="402" height="254" border="0" align="middle"
			alt="Cayenne Login Panel"/>
            
            <panel name="Note:">
            Use &quot;-nogui&quot; flag when calling runtests.sh if you need 
            to run tests in command line mode with no GUI (for example, for remote installations). 
            For things like automated unit tests "-xml [filename]" can be supplied on the command line
            to allow test script to read database info from an XML file.
            </panel>
                
            <p>Enter you
			database login information, JDBC driver class and database URL.
			JDBC driver class must be accessible by Java
			Virtual Machine. For example you can put a database vendor JAR
			file containing the driver in $JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/ext directory. 
	        Note that there is a combo box in the top left corner of the login panel
	        that allows user to select a canned driver and URL information. 
	        You must overwrite any of the canned data to provide the information that matches your
	        environment.
			</p>
			
			<p>Test results will be printed in a terminal window.</p>
        </subsection>
        
		<subsection name="2.5 Compiling Cayenne from Source" anchor="compile">
			<panel name="Note:">Normally users don't need to compile Cayenne. Prebuilt JAR's
			are included with both source and binary distributions.</panel>

			<p>For those users who need to recompile Cayenne (for example if they modified the
			source code to customize or test certain aspects), Cayenne source distribution
			provides Ant buildfile (<code>[cayenne_install_dir]/src/build.xml</code>). To build
			custom Cayenne jars execute the following commands. Windows:</p>

		<source>cd %CAYENNE_HOME%\src
%ANT_HOME%\bin\ant.bat</source>

		<p>UNIX</p>

		<source>cd $CAYENNE_HOME/src
$ANT_HOME/bin/ant</source>

			<p>Note that the original cayenne.jar file should be present in the
			<code>[cayenne_install_dir]/lib</code> directory, since it contains dependencies
			not included as a source code. The result of the build is two new JAR files:
			<code>[cayenne_install_dir]/lib/cayenne-cust.jar</code> and
			<code>[cayenne_install_dir]/lib/cayenne-tests-cust.jar</code>.
			</p>
		</subsection>
    </section>
</body>
</document>
